<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Levellers levelled to the very ground. Wherein this dangerous seditious opinion and design of some of them; that it is necessary, decent, and expedient, now to reduce the House of Peeres, and bring down the Lords into the Commons House, to sit and vote together with them, as one House. And the false absurd, grounds whereon they build this paradox, are briefly examined, refuted, and laid in the dust. / By William Prynne, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E428_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115569</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 67:E428[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Levellers levelled to the very ground. Wherein this dangerous seditious opinion and design of some of them; that it is necessary, decent, and expedient, now to reduce the House of Peeres, and bring down the Lords into the Commons House, to sit and vote together with them, as one House. And the false absurd, grounds whereon they build this paradox, are briefly examined, refuted, and laid in the dust. / By William Prynne, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Michael Spark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647 [i.e. 1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115569:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
LEVELLERS
Levelled to the very
GROUND. <hi>WHEREIN
This dangerous Seditious Opinion and deſign
of ſome of them;</hi> That it is neceſſary, decent,
and expedient, now to reduce the Houſe of Peeres, and
bring down the Lords into the Commons Houſe, to ſit and
Vote together with them, as one Houſe. And the falſe abſurd, grounds whereon they
build this <hi>Paradox,</hi> are briefly examined,
refuted, and laid in the duſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Prynne,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 19. 10.</bibl>
               <p>Delight is not ſeemly for a Foole; much leſſe for a Servant to rule
over Princes.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ECCLES. 10. 5, 7.</bibl>
               <p>There is an evill I have ſeen under the Sun, as an errour which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth
from the Ruler; I have ſeene Servants upon Horſes, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
walking as Servants upon the earth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Michael Spark.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115569:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115569:2"/>
            <head>THE
LEVELLERS
LEVELLED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine; and that
he likewiſe gave in ſpeciall charge to <hi>Titus</hi>
c. 3. 1. <hi>Put them in minde to be ſubject to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities
and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates, to bee
ready to every good work:</hi> But this Doctrine
now is little leſſe then <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and meere
<hi>Arbitrary Tyranny,</hi> in the opinion of a <hi>New
Generation</hi> of <hi>Levellers,</hi> and <hi>ſeditious Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi>
ſprung up among us ſince the Warres; the very perſons
of whom <hi>Peter</hi> prophecyed in the latter times;<note n="a" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Who deſpiſe
Dominion; preſumptuous, ſelfe-willed, they are not afraid to ſpeake
evill of Dignities, and the things that they underſtand not, and ſhall
periſh in their owne corruption.</hi> How active and induſtrious theſe
Fire-brands of Sedition have been by writing and petitioning
to extirpate <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Magiſtracy, Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry;</hi> and
how they move every ſtone to pull downe the Houſe of <hi>Peeres,</hi>
and levell the Lords to the Commoners, by bringing them
downe into the <hi>Commons-Houſe</hi> to ſit and vote together with
them as one, or elſe not to ſit or vote at all, is viſible to moſt;
and how many thouſands of ignorant ſimple people they
have ingaged to confederate with them in this pernicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne,
hath been already diſcovered in part to the Houſes; the
falſe ſuggeſtions and dangerous conſequencies whereupon it
is grounded, I ſhall ſuccinctly diſcover, to undeceive the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115569:3"/>
people, and take them off from ſuch a deſperate attempt,
which will prove deſtructive both to the Parliament, and
themſelves too in concluſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Lilburniſts</hi> and <hi>Levellers</hi> pretend, that it is not fit the
Lords ſhould fit and vote in a diſtinct Houſe by themſelves, as
they have done of latter times, but that they and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
ſhould now ſit all together in one Houſe, (to wit, the
Houſe of Commons, the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lilburns</hi> and <hi>Overtons</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, and late Letters. The agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people. The remonſtrance of many 1000 to their owne Houſe of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> ONELY SOVERAIGNE POW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER
OF THIS KINGDOME, as they ſtile it) as they did
of<note n="*" place="margin">Methinkes theſe <hi>New Lights</hi> ſhould not cry up and and revive old Preſidents &amp; Patterns, no more then old clothes, faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> old at firſt, and be new moulded into a ſingle Houſe; that
ſo Bills, Ordinances, Votes, and buſineſſes of Parliament
might paſſe with more expedition upon one Debate and Vote,
and not ſtay the Debates and Votes of two diſtinct Houſes ere
they be conſummate. And becauſe the Lords are but few in
number, the ſonnes of Conqueſt, not of election, repreſenting
onely themſelvs, but not the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> repreſented
onely by the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes choſen and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted
by them; therefore it is juſt and reaſonable the Lords
ſhould be levelled and brought down to the Commons Houſe
to ſit and Vote with them; and not enjoy any diſtinct or nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Votes among themſelves, as now they doe.</p>
            <p>To anſwer theſe pretences, I ſhall not inſiſt upon <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens Tit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Hon. par. 2. c 5 Spelm. Concil. Tom. 1. Mr. Lamb. Archa. Modus tenendi Parliamen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Truth triumphing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver falſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, p. 56. to 76. Cooks 9. Report, The Preface, &amp; 4. Inſt c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Lords
ancient and undoubted Right to ſit and Vote in Parliaments long before
the Conqueſt, from the firſt beginning of Parliaments to this preſent:</hi>
Nor on their activity and readineſſe in all ages, <hi>to oppoſe with
the loſſe and hazzard of their eſtates, heads, lives, the encroachments of
our Kings upon the Subjects Liberties, and vindicate the peoples free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
in the</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Mat. Pa. Mat. Weſtm. Walſingham, H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linſhed, Speed, Graf. on Truſſel, Daniel &amp; The. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 3. Par. of the Soveraign po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> 
               <hi>Reigns</hi> of King <hi>John, Henry</hi> the 3. <hi>Edward 2. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi>
2. and other <hi>oppreſſive Princes,</hi> againſt <hi>whoſe invaſions of
the Kingdomes Lawes and Rights they have ever beene the principall
Bulwarkes;</hi> and of late the chiefe procurers of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
and undertakers of our defenſive warre againſt the
King, wherein the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Lord <hi>Brook,</hi> Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi>
and others of them firſt appeared; Nor yet to debate their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
and undoubted power and right of <hi>Judicature</hi> in civill
and criminall caſes of Commoners as well as Peers, in all
times and Ages ſince there were Parliaments, of which there
are infinite preſidents in Hiſtories, Parliament Rols and Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls,
and ſundry diſclaimers of the whole Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
of being Judges in Parliament, as in 1. R. 2. <hi>Rot. Parl.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115569:3"/>
n. 38, 39, 40. 1 H. 7. Rot. Parl. n.</hi> 79. and <hi>Plac. Coronae. nu.</hi> 11. to 17.
and other Rolls: I ſhall wholly addreſſe my ſelfe to anſwer ſuch
Allegations as are moſt pertinent, touching the point of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
both Houſes into one, in ſuch manner as is projected.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I anſwer, what though it be probable by <hi>Modus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi
Parliamentum,</hi> that the King, Lords and Commons anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
ſat in one roome, and went in at one common doore in
<hi>King Edwards the Confeſſors</hi> time; yet it follows not, they all ſat
and voted together, as one intire houſe: no more then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows;
all the Judges and Officers of the Kings Courts of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi>
Kings <hi>Bench</hi> and <hi>Common Pleas</hi> ſit in one common Room,
and go in at one doore, at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall: therefore they all
ſit, judge and heare cauſes together, and are or ought to be
reduced to one Court; and do not judge, and heare cauſes
ſeverally, nor ought to do it: there being no one Author or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
of credit extant, which proves directly, that the Lords and
Commons did ever ſit, vote, or act together as one intire
houſe, and paſſe Billes, Judgements, Ordinances, Orders, by
one undivided and united Vote; the thing which ſhould be
proved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when, by whom, and upon what occaſion the
Houſes firſt came to be divided, is altogether uncertain, for
ought appeares by hiſtory or records.<note n="e" place="margin">4. Inſtit. p. 2. &amp;. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives,
that <hi>both houſes ſat together</hi> in 5. &amp; 6. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and that <hi>about
that ime, or a little after, they were firſt divided, when the Commons firſt
choſe a Speaker.</hi> But the Records of theſe Parliaments do not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily
warrant his conjecture herein; ſince they ſpeak only
of the meeting together of the three Eſtates in Parliament,
(as now they oft times do, on the firſt and laſt day of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
at conferences, paſſing Bills, and upon other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
not of their ſitting and voting together. For my part,
I conceive the diviſion of the Houſes farre more ancient, for
this reaſon, becauſe our hiſtorians writing of our ancienteſt
Parliaments, as well before as after the Conqueſt, do many
times make mention only of our<note n="f" place="margin">See Spelman Concil. T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1. Seldens titles of honour. par<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Kings, Archbiſhops, Biſhops,
Earles and Barons preſent in them,</hi> not of any <hi>Elders of the people,
Senators, Knights or Commons</hi> to repreſent the people, (which at
other times they ſpeak of) as preſent in our Parliaments,<note place="margin">Truth trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing over falſhood. <hi>p. 56. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
and Councells: occaſioned only as I conceive, by the
diſtinction of their ſitting places and debates. unleſſe it be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115569:4"/>
granted, that many of our ancient Parliaments were held
without Commons, Knights, and Burgeſſes, (as ſome affirm)
but never without Peers &amp; Lords; which would much invalid
the Commons authority, and that ſupream juriſdiction of theirs
which the <hi>Levellers</hi> now plead for. But admit they ſat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
in one roome in <hi>Edward</hi> the third his reigne, yet it is
cleart o me, their debates, votes, judgement, were long before
diſtinct as now they are, by that memorable paſſage in <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi>
(tranſcribed out of him by<note n="g" place="margin">Titles of Honour, part 2. Chap. 5. p. 705. 706</note> Maſter <hi>Selden;</hi> concerning the
jugdment given in Parliament at <hi>Northampton</hi> againſt <hi>Thomas
Becket</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the eleventh yeare of King
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1165. Where the <hi>Biſhops, Earles,
and all the Barons of England, reſolving upon the Kings motion there,
that</hi> Becket <hi>refuſing to appeare in Parliament, upon ſummons to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
the complaint againſt him, being neither hindered by ſickneſſe, nor
ſending any reaſonable excuſe for his not appearing,</hi> ſhould forſeit all
his moveable goods, and be at the Kings mercy: <hi>thereupon
there aroſe a difference between the Biſhops, and Barons, which of
them ſhould pronounce the judgement: the Barons alleadged, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
ought to pronounce it, becauſe he was a Biſhop, and they but Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;
the Biſhops Eccleſiaſticall perſons,</hi> and his fellow <hi>Priests, and
Biſhops. To which one of the Biſhops anſwered; it belonged to the Barons
and not to them, becauſe it was no Eccleſiaſticall but Secular judgement;
that they ſat there as</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Petrus Bleſenſis.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> De Inſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Epiſcopi B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bl. Patrum Tom. 12. pors 2. p. 447.</note> 
               <hi>Barons, not as Biſhops: you are</hi> Barons, <hi>and we
are</hi> Barons: <hi>here we are</hi> Peeres. <hi>But you inſiſt in vain upon the
reaſon of our Order: for if you regard in us our Ordination, you ought
likewiſe to conſider the ſame in him: Now in this that we are Biſhops,
we cannot judge our</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>and Lord. The King hearing this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie
about pronouncing the judgement, was moved, &amp; thereupon this
controverſie ceaſed: and the</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> (then Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
de Bloys) <hi>being at laſt enjoyned to give the judgement, pronounced
it againſt his will.</hi> There being no mention, ſpeech, or inter lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of the Commons in this whole Parliamentary debate
or cenſure, but onely of the King, Biſhops and Barons; it
makes it more then probable to me, that even then the Houſes
were divided; at leaſt, that they ſat and voted not together
but diſtinctly: and if the Commons were preſent, yet it is moſt
cleare, the Barons only were the Judges, and gave and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
the ſentence in Parliament, even without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.
Of which more in ſome other <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115569:4"/>
Thirdly; admit, the diviſion of the Houſes no ancienter then
King <hi>Edw.</hi> the third, yet their diviſion being made at firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
good grounds, to prevent confuſion and delayes, and to
paſſe things with more mature adviſe and deliberation upon
double debates, and ſecond cogitations, and continued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
ever ſince upon good grounds, without any alteration
oroppoſition. And this diviſion of them being ratified and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<hi>by the Law and cuſtome of Parliament,</hi> The Parl. Rolls,
and Journalls, yea confirmed by ſundry<note n="*" place="margin">And the Act for <hi>Trienniall Parliament,</hi> made this Parliament.</note> Acts of Parliament,
and among others by 31. <hi>H. 8. c. 10. 33. H. 8. c. 21. 3. Jac. c.</hi> 1. it can
be no way juſt, nor ſafe, nor convenient, nor honourable, to
confound them both together now, in the manner propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
yea a cleare diſſolving of the Parliament being contrary to
the Act for its continuance, &amp; a breach of the ſolemn League,
Covenant, and all engagements, to obey and defend BOTH
HOUSES OF PARLIAMENT; and a great diſhonour to
to the Lords, who cannot without apparent perjury and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy
ſubmit thereto: without whoſe full and free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents,
and the Kings too by ſpeciall act of Parliament, it is no
wayes feaſible, if by it,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it will introduce a world of contradictions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions,
abſurdities, and inconveniences, as theſe particulars
evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Firſt, both theſe houſes, as they are now divided, have,
(and alwayes ſince their diviſions have had) their ſeverall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
Speakers, and one chief cauſe of the diviſion (as<note n="h" place="margin">Inſtit. 4. p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> Sir
<hi>Edward Cook</hi> conceives) was the <hi>Commons</hi> chuſing <hi>of a continuall
Speaker.</hi> If then you will unite both Houſes into one; you muſt
have either theſe two Speakers in that one houſe (which
would breed confuſion and diſturbance, and be like two heads
upon one mans neck;) Or but one, both for Lords &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons,
who then cannot debate nor Vote diſtinctly, but joyntly
with the Commons. If but one, then which of the two ſhall
be the man? Not the Commons Speaker, becauſe they had no
Speaker at all before the Houſes were divided, &amp; ſo can claim
none when reunited. And the Lords Speaker being of greateſt
antiquity, Dignity, and Superiour to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in place and
degree, ought of right to be preferred, and enjoy the Speakers
place upon the reducement. And how a Peere; who is not<note n="*" place="margin">Cook 4. In<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtit. p. 8. 46. 47</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
either a Member or Speaker by the Commons, can by
the Law of the Land, or cuſtome of Parliament be Speaker of,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115569:5"/>
and for the Commons, as their mouth and repreſentative; or
a meere Commoner, a Speaker to the Lords to repreſent them,
tranſcends my Law and skill; and wil require 7 yeares time
to ſettle and reſolve. Secondly, if the Houſes be united, then
how and where ſhall the Lords, and their aſſiſtants ſit, and
how and where the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons? If all promiſcuouſly, this would
unlord, unpeere them, and make the meaneſt Commoner their
equall: If diſtinct, then why not in diſtinct Houſes ſtill, as well
as Claſſes and Seats? Or ſhall the Lords ſit covered and the
Commons ſit bare, as now they doat meetings and conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of both Houſes? This would be but ill Phyſick for the
Commons this winter ſeaſon, and too great a penance to ſuch
of them who have crazy heads, and weak legges, to ſtand bare
ſo long, and ſome of their ſpirits (eſpecially thoſe who are
the <hi>Levellers</hi> beſt friends) I doubt are ſo high, they would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
brook ſuch a pennance and daily obſervance. Thirdly, If
the Houſes be reduced into one, then their<note n="i" place="margin">Cook 4. Inſtit. p. 34. 35.</note> manner of voting
and dividing being diſtinct and different, as all know: the one
by a generall <hi>Ay,</hi> and <hi>No;</hi> the other by a particular <hi>Content</hi> and
not <hi>content,</hi> beginning at the puny Lord: the one determined by
dividing the Houſe, to take the Poll; the other without divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:
the one having no power to enter a Proteſtation of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
the other enjoying it: the one power to vote by Proxy,
the other onely in perſon without proxy: then whether ſhall
both retain theſe their differences ſtill in voting, which will
bring abſolute confuſion, and much delay: or elſe the Lords
vote as the Commons do, or the Commons as the Lords? If the
Lords only as Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moners, that were a diſparagement and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage
to them, and a meanes to deprive them of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
and votes as Peers, the Commons now having above
twenty to one for number. If the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons ſhall vote as Lords,
that would make them Peers; and make each Vote if given
particularly by the poll, &amp; the entring of proteſtations, ſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd
above half their time. Fourthly, if both houſes ſhould be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled
together, then the Lords alone muſt be judges, and
give Oathes and judgement as now they do, in writs of Error
and other cauſes, with which the Commons are not to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mddle;
or the Lords and Commons joyntly. If the Lords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
then why ſhould both Houſes be united, or they the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115569:5"/>
onely Judges in the Commons Houſe, or preſence, which their
greatneſſe doubtleſſe would not well digeſt? If Lords and
Commons joyntly, this would ſubvert and alter the ancient
proceedings and judgements of Parliament, and give the
Commons a new power of Judicature and giving Oathes, and
reverſing errours, they never claimed nor enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, if the Houſes be thus confounded, then what will
become of their diſtinct Servants, Officers, Clerkes, Doore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers,
&amp;c? Shall both continue? that were a ſuperfluity and
needleſſe charge: Shall one of them be diſcharged? then
whether the Lords on Commons? and whether the black
Rod will not be quite caſheered with the Lords houſe? will be
a greate queſtion, and require much time to reſolve. Sixtly,
if both Houſes be new-modelled into one, then what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
of all the Aſſiſtants of the Lords houſe? they certainly
muſt be caſhiered, eſpecially ſuch who are onely employed as
Meſſengers to the Commons Houſe, of which there will be
no uſe at all when they ſit together. Eighthly, what will
become of the forme of endorſing all Bils ſent from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
to the Lords: <hi>Soit bayle al Seignieurs: les Seigneurs ont
aſſentus:</hi> and the old forme of reading Bils thrice in both
Houſes ere they can paſſe them; and ſo of our Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?
In reſpect therefore of all theſe ſeverall contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and inconveniencies which can hardly be reconciled, and
no wayes altered, but by ſpeciall Act of Parliament (if by it)
without diſſolving the preſent Parliament, to pleaſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of ſeditious ignorant <hi>Lovellers</hi> and <hi>Sehiſmaticks,</hi> who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
pondered all theſe particulars; it can neither be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
nor ſafe to confound both Houſes together into one, as is
endeavoured and deſired.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, the Act of 16. <hi>Caroli Regis,</hi> entituled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>An Act for the
preventing of inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veniences, happening by the long intermiſſions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments;</hi>
(made with abundance of care and pains this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
before the King's departure) diſtingueſheth the houſe of
Commons from the houſe of Lords; preſcribes an oath <hi>in haec
verba,</hi> to the Lord Chancell our, Lord Keeper, and Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners
of the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> You ſhall ſwear, that you
ſhall truly and faithfully iſſue out, and ſend abroad all Writs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115569:6"/>
of Summons to Parliament FOR BOTH HOUSES.
And <hi>in default thereof, enacts, That THE PEERS of this
Realm ſhall be enabled and ENJOYNED to meet in the old Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace
of</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>AT THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALL PLACE
THERE, on the third Monday on November: and that they, or any
twelve or more of them THEN AND THERE AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEMBLED
ſhall iſſue out Writs in uſuall form, under the hands
and ſeals of twelve or more of them, to the reſpective Sheriffs, and
other Officers, for the electing of Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes of
Parliament.</hi> That on the third Monday in <hi>January,</hi> and ſecond
Tueſday in <hi>March,</hi> ALL AND EVERY THE
PEERS OF THE REALM <hi>ſhall make their appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
and aſſembly at</hi> THE PALLACE <hi>aforeſaid; and ſhall</hi>
EACH OF THEM <hi>be liable unto ſuch pains and cenſures
for his and their</hi> NOT APPEARING AND SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VING
<hi>then and</hi> THERE <hi>in Parliament, as if be or they had
been ſummoned by Writ under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>and had not
appeared and ſerved, and to ſuch further pains and cenſures as</hi> BY
THE REST OF THE PEERS <hi>in Parliament
aſſembled</hi> THEY SHALL BE JUDGED UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO:
<hi>And that the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes aſſembled</hi> IN
THE COMMONS HOUSE <hi>of Parliament, ſhall be
liable to ſuch pains and cenſures as he or they ſhall be adjudged unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it enacts, <hi>That neither the</hi> HOUSE OF PEERS
<hi>nor</hi> THE HOUSE OF COMMONS <hi>ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed
within fifty dayes at leaſt, after the meeting thereof, unleſſe it
be by the free conſent</hi> OF EVERY THE SAID HOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES
RESPECTIVELY: <hi>And that the</hi> PEERS
<hi>aſſembled in Parliament, may</hi> FROM TIME TO TIME
<hi>chooſe and declare ſuch perſon</hi> TO BE SPEAKER FOR
THE SAID PEERS <hi>as they ſhall think fit: And that the
ſaid Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, ſhall and may</hi> FROM
TIME TO TIME DURING THEIR AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEMBLY
IN PARLIAMENT, <hi>chooſe and declare
one of themſelves to be</hi> SPEAKER OF THE HOUSE
OF COMMONS, <hi>as they ſhall think fit: VVhich ſaid</hi>
SPEAKERS, <hi>as well for the ſaid</hi> PEERS <hi>as</hi> HOUSE
OF COMMONS RESPECTIVELY, <hi>ſhall be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115569:6"/>
perfect and conpleat Speakers</hi> FOR THE SAID HOVSES RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SPECTIVELY,
<hi>and ſhall have as full and large power, juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
and priviledges, to all intents and purpoſes, as any</hi> SPEAKER
OR SPEAKERS OF EITHER OF THE SAID HOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES
RESPECTIVELY <hi>heretofore have had and enjoyed.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the levelling and reducing of both Houſes into one, or
aboliſhing the Lords Houſe and Peerage, will utterly null and
repeal this Act, (the beſt that was ever yet made for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
ſafety, and Parliaments advantage) and deprive both
Parliament, Kingdome and people of all future benefit by it,
(which I wiſh our <hi>Levellers</hi> and <hi>Lilburniſts</hi> ſeriouſly to conſider)
and likewiſe null and repeal the Act to <hi>prevent Inconveniences
which may happen by the untimely adjourning, proroguing or diſſolving of
this preſent Parliam.</hi> An. 17. <hi>Car.</hi> which enacts, <hi>That</hi> THE HOUSE
OF PEERS <hi>ſhal not at any time or times be adjourned during the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
Parliament, unleſſe it be</hi> BY THEMSELVES OR THEIR
OWN ORDER: <hi>And in like manner, that</hi> THE HOUSE
OF COMMONS <hi>ſhall not at any time or times during this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
be adjourned, unleſſe it be</hi> BY THEMSELVES, OR BY
THEIR OWN ORDER. Which I hope both Houſes, as
they deſire their own continuance, and being of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
will well adviſe of; and all thoſe whom <hi>Lilburn</hi> or his
Emiſſaries have ſeduced to engage againſt the Houſe of Lords,
or levell them to the Commons.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, admit the Houſes might without any inevitable
miſchiefes and contradictions, be modeled, and united into
one, yet to bring downe the Lords into the Commons Houſe,
to ſit and Vote like Commons with them, is no wayes tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
or to be thought on but with indignation, for theſe
reaſons. Firſt, becauſe the whole Commons Houſe it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
when they preſent their Speaker to the King and Lords (which
will be aboliſhed by this union) or when any Bills are to be
paſſed by the Royall Aſſent, upon the<note n="k" place="margin">Cook 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Inſt. p.</hi> 28. 33 H. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 21. 3 Jac. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>beginning</hi> and ending of
every Parliament, and upon ſome other ſpeciall occaſions
have alwayes uſed to goe up and wait upon the Houſe of
Lords in perſon, yea to ſtand bare at their Barre, and to ſend
their Members in perſon<note n="*" place="margin">See 5. R. 2. n. 16.</note> up to the Lords upon any Meſſage,
Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, or other occaſion; but never did the whole Houſe of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115569:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115569:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115569:8"/>
Peeres in any age come downe in perſon to the Commons
Houſe, or any Peeres of late bring Meſſages to them, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſend them by ſome Aſſiſtants, as <hi>Judges, Maſters of Chancery, &amp;c.</hi>
Therefore now to talk of bringing down the Houſe of Peeres
to ſit with the Commons in their Houſe, (all one, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
a Noble mans Dining-roome to his Hall or Kitchin, and
levell the roofe and upper roomes of a houſe with the lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
floore) is ſuch a diſhonour and affront to the Lords,
that none but degenerate and ignoble ſpirits can ſo much as
heare or think of it with patience, nor no Peere reſent it but
with juſt ſcorne and contempt, and rather dye then conſent
unto it, without whoſe conſents it cannot be done without
both Houſes ruine: And to bring up the Houſe of Commons
to ſit and Vote joyntly with the Peeres, would be to advance
the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> above their degree, not <hi>level the Lords;</hi> to make ſome
men <hi>Lords</hi> before they are <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> &amp; every <hi>Commoner</hi> no leſſe
then a <hi>Lord,</hi> which would too much puffe and bladder them
with pride, and make them ſlight thoſe whom they repreſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
who being but <hi>Commoners,</hi> cannot be repreſented by <hi>Peeres,</hi>
or any ſitting and Voting in the <hi>Houſe of Peeres,</hi> by the true
fundamental Law and Cuſtome of Parliaments, as Sir<note n="l" place="margin">Inſtit. 4. p. 8, 46, 47.</note> 
               <hi>Edward
Cooke</hi> reſolves. Secondly, if the Lords ſhould bee brought
downe into the Commons Houſe, (which is much like the
reducing of the head and ſhoulders of the naturall body,
into the belly or legges, which would make a Monſter and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
the man) there would be no roome for them, their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
and Aſſiſtants, unleſſe enlarged and metamorphoſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
another forme. Thirdly, If the Lords muſt bee brought
downe into the Commons Houſe, then the<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Cook<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 4. Inſt. p. 14, 15.</note> King and Prince
as well as they, or elſe they muſt be totally excluded the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
or ſit alone by themſelves in the Houſe of Lords,
without any Lords to attend them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> An indignity which no
King or Prince can brooke, and no modeſt Commoner ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
thinke of but with deteſtation; nor Lord, nor King
conſent to, but by force and violence; and without their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
conſents it will not be valid, but deſtructive.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The falſe pretext for it, of expediting <hi>Bills, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi>
and <hi>Votes,</hi> is an abſurd and ignorant fancie of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115569:8"/>
ſpirits, who would act all things in a hurry without
good deliberation: For firſt, nothing ought to bee done in
Parliament but upon full and mature debate and deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of all the circumſtances and probable conſequences of it
in future time (a thing now ſeldome conſidered:) <hi>Diu delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum
quod ſemel ſtatuendum, &amp;, Feſtina lente,</hi> are ſafe rules in
Parliament, eſpecially in paſſing publike Acts and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
in making Warre or Peace, or any Nationall Leagues and
Agreements. Secondly, <hi>Haſty Dogges bring forth blinde Whelpes:</hi>
and haſty Votes, over ſudden Councels and Motions, lame,
blinde, contradictory, unjuſt, and inconſiderate Orders, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,
Acts, which muſt either be corrected, ſupplyed, or
repealed by Additionals, of which we have had too many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
ſince this Parliament; which in many Votes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,
Orders, and Impeachments hath made more haſte
then good ſpeed; and Voted ſometimes both abſurdities and
impoſſibilities (witneſſe the <hi>Commons</hi> Votes, for the Tryall of
<hi>Mac-Guire and Mac-Mohun in the Kings-Bench, the very firſt day of
the Terme,</hi> before any Indictment drawne, found, or any Jury
ſummoned to finde it; for the Tryall of Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> in the
<hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> by a ſhort day, for Treaſon aleaged to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
in <hi>Wales,</hi> before any Indictment found in the Country,
or removed into Court, and the like;) which I only mention
to ſatisfie and anſwer the Objectors, nor to defame the Houſe
or Houſes, whoſe Honours and Reputations have beene much
blemiſhed, through the inconſiderate raſhneſſe of ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
Members, who poaſted on ſuch Votes and Impeachments.
Thirdly, this dividng the Houſes will breed infinite diſorder
and confuſion,<note n="*" place="margin">4. Inſtit. q. 2.</note> not expedition, in their proceedings, as the
premiſes manifeſt, and deſtroy their very formes and method;
upon which ground Sir<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſſe Dr <hi>Levtons,</hi> Dr. <hi>Baſtwicks,</hi> Mr <hi>Burtons,</hi> my own, Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys,</hi> the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterwars</hi> and many others, about Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> 
               <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> writes they were firſt
divided. Fourthly, it will be a great retarding and obſtruction
to publike Juſtice, eſpecially in Writs of Errour, and all ſuch
things which the Lords may diſpatch or judge without the
Commons Houſe; where many <hi>hundreds of Petitions and buſineſſes
heard and Voted above ſeven yeeres ſince,</hi> doe yet ſtick without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,
or tranſmiſſion to the Lords (to the great diſhonour and
ſcandall of their proceedings and ſpeedy juſtice) which had
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115569:9"/>
been diſpatched and ended many years paſt, had they firſt peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
to the Lords for redreſſe. So as the Lords Houſe is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
no cauſe of delay, but the Commons rather, through their
long debates or want of method, which debates would bee
increaſed and lengthned by adding of the Lords unto them,
who can now debate and determine things apart, and reſolve
two or three things, or more, whiles the Commons are deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
one: And therefore, if delay be the onely cauſe of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
the Lords Houſe to the Commons, the Commons cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
are rather to be reduced then the Lords, and may bee
better ſpared of the two (even by<note n="k" place="margin">His letter to a friend, his letters to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Martyn</hi> and <hi>Cromwel,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and Truth juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Englands</hi> Birth-right, the late Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many free-born peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lilburnes</hi> and his <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates
Libells</hi> and <hi>Petitions</hi>) their delayes being not a quarter
to one ſo many, nor one quarter ſo long as the <hi>Commons,</hi> as
themſelves muſt and do acknowledge. Eightly, this whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
is a direct breach of the ſolemn League and Covenant, a
ſubverſion of the Law and Cuſtome of Parliaments, a device
to deſtroy both Houſes, under pretext of reducing them into
one; an engine to diſſolve this preſent, and all future Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
to alter the fundamentall Lawes and Government of
this Kingdom, to unking the King, unprince the Prince, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord
the Lords, and quite deſtroy their Houſe (almoſt effected
by expulſions, and impeachments of moſt of their Members
by degrees, who have ſcarce enough left to make up an houſe,
which it is high time for them &amp; the Commons to obſerve;)
yea, a project to extirpate Monarchy and Nobility, and ſet up a
popular Anarchy and Polarchy: And therfore who ever hath
plotted and fomented it, is more guilty of high Treaſon then
<hi>Strafford, Canterbury,</hi> or the Gun-powder Traitors, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
a ſeverer puniſhment then they underwent, even by the
hands of the Parliament it ſelf, and all that are wel-wiſhers
to Parliaments or Kingdom, though no friends to Peers.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, this diviſion of the Houſes is; Firſt, a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
to the Parliament and Houſes, ſavouring of greater Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
State, and Order, then their joyning into one, and giving
every eſtate its<note n="*" place="margin">31 H. 8. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> du<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place and ranke. Secondly, a great eaſe
and benefit to the Subject, who may make his Addreſſes and
Petitions to either at his election for reliefe. Thirdly, a great
diſpatch and expedition to all publike affaires, one Houſe fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115569:9"/>
and preparing them for the Debat, &amp; concurrence of the
other, at one and the ſame time, as Committees of each
Houſe prepare and expedite buſineſſes for the whole Houſe.
Fourthly, a means of more ſpeedy juſtice, by the Commons
preparing of Articles and evidence for complaints and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments,
preſented by them to the Lords, whiles they are
diſpatching other buſineſſes; and their hearing Writs of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
and other cauſes, whiles the Commons are upon other
debates; which they could not do in one houſe, but joyntly
together, and ſucceſſively, not with ſo quick diſpatch, and ſuch
good order as now. Fifthly, a thing very neceſſary and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious
to the Kingdom and people, and ſafeſt for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
in that the Lords upon their ſecond debates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
with the Judges and others, many times amend and
rectifie divers errours, imperfections, and miſtakes in the over-haſty Votes, yea &amp; deliberate Orders, Ordinances, Bils and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations
of the Commons, which the Commons acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
by their aſſents unto their amendments; and oft times
the Commons ſtay ſome Votes, Orders, Bils, Ordinance,
ſent down to them by the Lords; and their ſeveral amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and diſlikes, with the conferences and debates occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
thereupon, and ſecond conſiderations of Buſineſſes, Votes,
Ordinances, Orders, Bils, Declarations, and the like, make
them more profitable, compleat and valid, and leſſe liable to
exceptions and evaſions then elſe they would have been. In
all which reſpects, this diviſion of the Houſes, and the Lords
and Kings negative voyces rightly conſidered and uſed, are
not onely convenient, but expedient and abſolutely neceſſary
for the publike good, whatever <hi>Lilburn</hi> and his ignorant Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers
fancy to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall therefore cloſe up this with that wholeſome and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
advice of</hi> Solomon, Prov. 24. 21, 22. My ſonne feare thou
the Lord and the King, and meddle not with thoſe WHO ARE GI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN
TO CHANGE; For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and
who knoweth the ruine of them both?</p>
            <p>There is onely one Objection to be removed,<note place="margin">Object.</note> wherewith I
ſhall arme the Levellers, that ſo I may leave nothing unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115569:10"/>
that may be hereafter inſiſted on. And that is, this
paſſage in <hi>Modus tenendi Parliamentum, We muſt know, that for the
granting of ſuch help and ayd (to the King) it hehooveth</hi> THAT ALL
THE PEERS OF THE PARLIAMENT AGREE: <hi>And we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand,
that two Knights which come to the Parliament for the Shiers
and Countries out of which they come, have a greater voyce in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
TO GRANT, <hi>then</hi> THE GREATEST EARL <hi>in</hi>
England: <hi>And after the ſame manner the Procters for the Clergie, or
Clerks of the Convocation-houſe for one Biſhoprick, have a greater
voyce in Parliament, if they all agree, then the Biſhop himſelf: And this
is true in all things which ought to be granted or denyed to the party, or
are to be done therein. And this is manifeſt,</hi> BECAUSE THE KING
MAY HOLD A PARLIAMENT WITH THE COMMOMALTY AND
COMMONS OF THE KINGDOM WITHOUT BISHOPS, EARLS
AND BARONS; <hi>yet ſo, as they be ſummoned to the Parliament, although
no Biſhop, Earl or Baron come according to their ſummons:</hi> BECAUSE
IN TIMES PAST, NEITHER WAS THERE BISHOP, EARL OR
BARON; <hi>and yet</hi> EVEN THEN KINGS KEPT THEIR PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT.
<hi>But it is far otherwiſe on the other ſide; for though the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty,</hi>
to wit, <hi>Laity and Clergie were ſummoned to the Parliament
(as of right they ought to be) yet for ſome certain cauſes they would not
come; as if they did pretend, that the King did not govern them as he
ought, and in ſpeciality point out the Articles in which he miſgoverned
them, as he ought;</hi> TUNC PARLIAMENTUM NULLUM EST OM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NINO;
<note n="l" place="margin">So the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh being non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſlated in many places.</note> 
               <hi>then there is no Parliament at all, though all the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops,
Biſhops, Earls and Barons, and and all the Peers ſhould be preſent
with the King: And therefore it behooveth that all things which ought
to be affirmed or informed, granted or done by the Parliament, ſhould
be granted by the Commonalty of the Parliament; which conſists of three
degrees or kinds aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> to wit, <hi>of the Practors of the
Clergie, the Knights of the Shires, the Citizens and Burgeſſes, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
the whole Commonalty of</hi> England, <hi>and not of Noble men; becauſe
every one of them is for his own proper perſon preſent at the Parliament,
and for no other: Which Master</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Holinſhead</hi> Chron. of <hi>Irel.</hi> p. 127, 128.</note> John Vowel <hi>in his Order and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
how to keep a Parliament;</hi> ſeconds in theſe words:</p>
            <p>If the King in due order have ſummoned all his Lords and Barons,
and they will not come; or if they come, they will not yet appear; or if
they come and appear, and will not doe no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yeeld to any things THEN
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115569:10"/>
THE KING WITH THE CONSENT OF THE COMMONS
MAY ORDAIN AND ESTABLISH ANY ACTS OR LAWS
WHICH ARE AS GOOD, S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FFICIENT AND EFFECT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALL,
AS IF THE LORDS HAD GIVEN THEIR CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENTS.
But on the contrary, if the Commons be ſummoned, and will
not come; or comming will not appear, or appearing will not conſent to
do any thing, alledging ſome juſt, weighty or great cauſe, the King in
thoſe caſes cannot with the Lords deviſe, make or establiſh any Law.
<hi>The reaſons are theſe;</hi> When Parliaments were firſt began and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,
there were no Prelates or Barons of the Parliament, and the
temporal Lords were very few or none, and then the<note n="*" place="margin">In what age was there ever ſuch a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King and Commons onely?</note> King and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
did make a full Parliament; <hi>which authority was NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VER
YET ABRIDGED. Again, every Baron in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
doth repreſent his own perſon, and ſpeaketh in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half
of himſelf alone; but in the Knights, Citizens and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes,
are repreſented the Commons of the whole Realm;
and every of theſe giveth conſent, not onely for himſelf, but
for all thoſe alſo for whom he is ſent: And the King with
the conſent of the Commons,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">A groſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake without preſident to warrant it.</note> HAD EVER A S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FFICI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENT
AND F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THORITY TO MAKE, ORDAIN
AND ESTABLISH GOOD AND WHOLSOME LAWS FOR
THE COMMON-WEALTH OF THE REALM: <hi>Wherefore
the Lords being lawfully ſummoned, and yet refuſing to come,
ſit or conſent in Parliament,</hi> CANNOT BY THEIR FOLLY
ABRIDGE THE KING OR THE COMMONS OF THEIR
LAWF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL PROCEEDINGS IN PARLIAMENT. <hi>So he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which two paſſages it may be probably inferred; firſt,
that a Parliament may now be held, and Acts and Laws made
by the King and Commons alone, without the Lords; but not
by the King and Lords without the Commons; and ſo their
ſitting in Parliament is not ſimply neceſſary, ſo as they may
quite be taken away and reduced to the Commons houſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
that they have no negative voice, but ought to aſſent
to whatever the Commons ſhall vote to be good and neceſſary
for the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer;<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> firſt, that the compiler of the firſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,
is both unknown, &amp; the time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was firſt compiled, not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115569:11"/>
ſo ancient as is imagined by ſome hundreds of yeers: It is ſaid
in the preface, it was firſt compoſed in <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor's
time, and ſhewed to <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, &amp; approved and
uſed by him: but he that made this Preface to it (addes) <hi>That
it was uſed IN THE TIMES OF HIS S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CCESSORS KINGS
OF</hi> ENGLAND, and therefore lived long after the Conquerours
time) and ſo writes but at random, not of his own knowledge,
there being no Hiſtory nor Record to warrant any ſuch thing:
and by his Diſcourſe touching the Members places and ſitting
in Parliament, manner of Marſhalling the Biſhops and others,
and by other paſſages, it ſhould ſeem, a great part of this
Treatiſe is but of late compoſure: As for its exemplification
by King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and his ſending it into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and his ſending it into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth his exemplification of it there, I find no
warrant for it, but Sir<note n="o" place="margin">Inſtit. 4. p. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Edward Cooks</hi> aſſertion, and that
grounded upon a bare report from another: theſe exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations
(for ought I can learn) being neither of them extant,
nor yet ſo much as once mentioned by Maſter <hi>Richard Bolton</hi>
(a great Antiquary) in his <hi>Collection of the Statutes of Ireland:</hi>
Beſides, the election of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders grand Inqueſt. p. 5, 10 16.</note> two Knights to ſerve for every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
two Citizens for every City, and two Burgeſſes for every
Burrough, and the Procurators of the Clergy, cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
by any Hiſtory or Records extant, to be formally choſen
by Writ, and ſent to the Parliament, in <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſors
reign; nor that all thoſe aſſiſtants w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> this Treatiſe mentions
did then ſit or were preſent in Parliaments, in ſuch manner &amp;
form as is expreſſed in this Treatiſe: Yea, the very objected
paſſage, &amp; reaſon therin rendered, proves it ſelf to be of pun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er
date then the Confeſſors or Conquerours dayes. Secondly,
admit it as ancient as the Confeſſor or Conquerour, then it is
apparent, that even in thoſe times the Houſes either ſate not,
at leaſt voted not both together, as is pretended: For firſt, this
<hi>Treatiſe distinguiſheth the Biſhops, Earls and Barons, as distinct ranks
and degrees of Parliament, both from Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes,
throughout the Treatiſe:</hi> Secondly, it diſtinguiſheth them in the
<hi>times and dayes of their calling in the beginning of the Parliament, and
in their fines for not appearing:</hi> Thirdly, in the <hi>charge the King gives
to them:</hi> Fourthly, in the <hi>places and manner of their ſitting, all the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115569:11"/>
ſeverall orders of Peers, and Aſſistants of the Lords houſe being menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,
as ſitting together, without any Knights, Citizens or Burgeſſes
ſitting among them.</hi> And he addes, <hi>that between the Biſhops, Earls,
Barons, all muſt keep their places, and the Steward of</hi> England <hi>is to
look to this, THAT NONE SIT B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T AMONG HIS PEERS
AND EQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALS:</hi> Fiftly, he ſubjoyns, <hi>That the Justices of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<hi>are no Justices in Parliament, unleſſe ſo far forth as new power
ſhall be aſſigned and given them then by the KING AND THE
PEERS of the Parliament: That the Peers of the Parliament are
to examine Petitions BY THEMSEVES: That the King ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
five skilfull Clerks of the Parliament: the firſt whereof ſhall be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
to ſerve the Biſhops; the ſecond, the Procters of the Clergie; the
third, the Earls and Barons; the fourth, the Knights of the Shire; the
fift, the Citizens and Burgeſſes: who ſhall write and register their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
anſwers and doubts to the King; that all doubtfull caſes are to be put
in writing, and delivered to the Clerk of every degree; that ſo every DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GREE
BY IT SELF MAY GOE THERE BY IT SELFE
AND DEBATE IT, and then bring their ANSWER AND AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VICE
IN WRITING; and if any diſcord ariſe, that the buſineſſe
be handled and amended by all the Peers of the Kingdom: And that none
of all the Peers may depart from Parliament, unleſſe he have obtained
leave</hi> OF THE KING, <hi>and of</hi> ALL HIS PEERS. All which
proves the deviſion and diſtinction of the Houſes in that Age,
in Votes and Debates.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, both theſe Writers grant; Firſt, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
can doe or conclude nothing without the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
and conſent: Secondly, that all the Lords ought to be
ſummoned to the Parliament, and if they appear not, that
they ſhall be amerced: Thirdly, that <hi>ALL PEERS OF
THE REALME O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT TO AGREE TO WHAT IS
GRANTED OR PASSED IN PARLIAMENT;</hi> ſo are their
words: Therefore if all the Peers, or the major part of them
diſagree, no ayde can be granted nor Act paſſed, by their
own confeſſions: and by the ſame reaſon they affirm, that the
King and Lords, or either of them alone, without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
can grant or enact nothing that is firme or ſtable;
nor yet the Commons themſelves without the Kings aſſent;
they muſt of neceſſity grant, that the King and Commons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115569:12"/>
without the Lords can do nothing, that is binding to the
Kingdom, the Lords aſſent being as requiſite as theirs, and they
entruſted by the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtome of the Realm, to
conſent and diſſent in the granting of aydes, and making
Laws as well as the King and Commons, and have a ſhare inboth
as well as they.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the holding of a Parliament, granting of aydes
and making Laws by the King and Commons, without the
Lords, is onely in one ſpeciall caſe of obſtinacy and extremity
in the Lords; which never yet fell out, nor is likely to happen:
To wit, <hi>when the Lords are all ſummoned to Parliament, and yet wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
refuſe to appear, ſit or agree to any thing propounded by the King
and Commons joyntly, without giving a ſufficient reaſon for their ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi>
To conclude therefore from ſuch a remote poſſibility of
a caſe which never yet fell out, nor is likely to do, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
of the Lords reducement at this preſent, or in future
times to the Houſe of Commons, or the abolition of the Houſe
of Peers, or their negative voyce, is as great nonſence and fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy,
as to argue; that all the Lords and Commons ought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
to be ſent to <hi>Bedlam,</hi> becauſe one of our Parliaments
was ſtiled, <hi>Inſanum Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, The mad Parliament,</hi> and they
may poſſibly prove now as mad as the Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted;
as they will do in good earneſt, if they ſhould go about
to levell the Lords, and detrude them to the Commons houſe,
as theſe mad Sectaries and Levellers would perſwade them.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, neither of theſe Writers were good Lawyers, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians
or Antiquaries verſed in Parliament Records: for firſt,
our<note n="o" place="margin">22 E. 3. 3. <hi>b.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H. 7. 14. 11 H 7. 27 <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Parl.</hi> 107. Plowdens <hi>Cou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 79. Crompton's <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, f.</hi> 8. Forteſcue, <hi>c. 18 f.</hi> 20. 4 H. 7. 6. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Dy</hi> 92. Bro. 134, 39 E. 3. 7.</note> Law-books are expreſſe in point, <hi>That no Law nor Act of
Parliament can be made by the King and Commons without the Lords
concurrent aſſent, no more then by the King and Lords without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons:</hi>
And Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> (the greateſt Lawyer in this latter
age) is poſitive, in his 4. <hi>Inst.</hi> c. 1. (where he writes particularly
of Parliaments) f. 25. <hi>There is NO ACT OF PARLIAMENT
B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST HAVE CONSENT OF THE LORDS, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
and royall aſſent of the King, as appeareth by RECORDS AND
O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R LAW-BOOKS:</hi> Therefore this fancy of theirs, <hi>that the
King and Commons may make Laws without the Lords,</hi> is a cleer
miſtake even in point of Law; which the very form and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115569:12"/>
of all our Statutes (<hi>Be it enacted by the King, &amp;c. THE
LORDS SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALL AND TEMPORALL, and Commons in
this preſent Parliament aſſemblea;</hi> and the like) refutes: Secondly,
all our Hiſtorians and Antiquaries concur herein, That there
can be no Parliament, nor ever was in any age ſince Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
were in <hi>England,</hi> held by the King and Commons alone
without the Lords; there being no ſuch Parliament ever heard
or read of, neither do theſe Authors inſtance in any one Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent;
therefore this ground of their opinion, <hi>That in times paſt
our Kings kept their Parliaments, when &amp; before there were any B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhops
or temporall Lords,</hi> is a meer groundleſſe aſſertion, contradicted
by all our Antiquaries and Hiſtorians; which alwayes make
mention of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Dukes, Princes,
Earls, Lords and Barons in our ancienteſt Parliaments,
but<note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> Titles of Honour, part 2. c. 5. <hi>Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manni</hi> Concil. Tom. 1. Truth triumphing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver falſhood, p 50, to 70. The grand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, p. 8, to 16.</note> no mention at all of any Knights of Shires, Citizens and
Burgeſſes: Thirdly, all our Parliament Rolls contradict this
fancy, that there can be no Act nor Ordinance of Parliament
without the Lords conſent as well as the Commons; as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
by the penning of all our printed Acts, and by 6 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.
Rot. Parl. n. 5. 17 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 59, 60. 43 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 3, &amp; 10. 14 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n.
14, 15. 13 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 25. with many more: yea, the Lords preſence
in Parliament hath at all times be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſo <hi>abſolutely neceſſary and
expedient; that our Parliaments from time to time have been adjourned
from the day that they were firſt appointed to ſit, till ſome few days after;</hi>
upon this very reaſon, <hi>That</hi> ALL THE LORDS (<hi>by reaſon of the foul
weather, ſhortneſſe of ſummons, or ſome other occaſion) were not yet come
up to the Parliament, OR SOME OF THE LORDS NOT
COME; and the Declaration of the cauſes of calling the Parliament by
the Lord Chancellour, or chief Justice, and all Parliamentary buſineſſe
deferred till their comming, (as well as becauſe ſome of the Knights and
Burgeſſes were not come, nor all the Writs for their elections returned:)
upon which reaſon, and the abſence of ſome Lords, the firſt day of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments
ſitting, hath been oft adjourned,</hi> as the Parliament
Rolls of 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. nu. 1. 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 2. n. 5, 6, 8, 9. 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 2. n.
4. 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 5. 17 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 2. 6. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1, 2, 5. 20 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 5. 21 <hi>E.</hi>
3. n. 4. 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 29 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 4. 36 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 37 <hi>E.</hi>
3. n. 1. 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 51 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 3. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 1, 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n.
1. 3 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 1. 4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 1. 5 <hi>R.</hi> 2. Parl. 1. n. 1. &amp; Parl. 2. n. 1. 6 <hi>R.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115569:13"/>
2. Parl. 1. n. 1. &amp; Parl. 2. n. 1. abundantly<note n="*" place="margin">And 8 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 28, 30, 54. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 1. 1; <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 1.</note> manifeſt, it being the
cuſtome of all former Parliaments to Debate, Vote and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
nothing but in <hi>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL PARLIAMENT,</hi> when all, or the
moſt part of the Members of both Houſes were preſent, and
not in a thin or empty Houſe, when above half or three parts
were abſent: an innovation of dangerous conſequence, brought
in of later times, and fit to be redreſſed, <hi>for which ſome Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and Parliamentary proceedings have been</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">See 31 <hi>F.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. n. 16. 1 <hi>H</hi> 4. Rot. Parl. 22, 25, 66. 39 <hi>H.</hi> 6. c. 1. Statutes of <hi>Ireland, 10 H</hi> 7. c. 23. 21 <hi>R.</hi> 2. c. 12. 31 <hi>H</hi> 6 c. 1. 17 <hi>E.</hi> 4. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>repealed and judged
voyd by Parliament;</hi> eſpecially when accompanied with any
armed forces and violence, over-awing the Houſes or their
Members: to prevent which in former ages, by the<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cook</hi> 4 Inſt. p. 14 &amp; 2 <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
law and custome of Parliament, a Proclamation uſually was and
ought to be made at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>in the beginning of every Parliament
THAT NO MAN, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON PAIN TO LOSE ALL THAT HE
HAD, SHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RING THE PARLIAMENT, in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<hi>or</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>or the Suburbs, &amp;c. wear any privy coat of Plate,
OR GOE ARMED, or uſe any Games, Playes, Justs, and other
paſtimes, or ſhewing Shewes during the Parliament: The reaſon whereof
was, That the high Court of Parliament ſhould not thereby be diſturbed,
nor the Members thereof (which are TO ATTEND the arduous and
urgent buſineſſe of the Church and Common-wealth) be thereby</hi> WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DRAWN
OR FORCED AWAY: as is apparent by 5 <hi>E.</hi>
3. nu. 5. 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. nu. 2, 3. 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 2. n. 2. 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 4. n. 4, 5.
13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 21. n. 2. 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 2. 17 <hi>E.</hi>
3. n. 3. 20 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 24 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 1. 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 5, 8. &amp; Stat. 2. n. 4. A
law and cuſtome now fit to be revived. Fourthly, the very
Writs of Summons for the Lords, and of election of Knights,
Citizens and Burgeſſes, refutes this groſſe miſtake, requiring
them all <hi>to appear perſonally in Parliament, on ſuch a day, at ſuch a
place, and there to treat of the great and urgent affairs of the Realm, not
onely with the King himſelf, but</hi> cum Praelatis, MAGNATIBUS
ET PROCERIBUS dicti Regni noſtri; <hi>with the Prelates, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen
and Lords of our ſaid Realm:</hi> And therefore to dream of
holding a Parliament, or making Lawes without the Lords,
is a ſign of an intoxicated brain. Fiftly, I find in 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. nu.
58. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 60. 37 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 12, 34. 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 12, 13. and the
yeer-book of 39 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 7. b. that <hi>the King and Lords in Parliament</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See the Free holders grand Inqueſt.</note> 
               <hi>have made binding laws without the Commons, in ſome caſes, but not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115569:13"/>
the King and Commons without the Lords:</hi> And in the Parliament
of 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 2. n. 7. <hi>the Commons had licenſe to depart the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
but the Lords were commanded to attend the King the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
to adviſe him:</hi> So that there is far more colour in point of
Preſidents to prove, that the King and Lords may make Laws
and grants of aydes, (as the Lords did by and for themſelves,
3 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 4, 5. &amp; Parl. 2. 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 7.) without the Commons,
then the King and Commons without the Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixtly, to this,</hi> that the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes in parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
have a greater voyce then the greateſt Earl in parliament, becauſe
they repreſent the Countries, Cities and Burroughs from whence they
come, and the Earl but himſelf.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, firſt, that the reaſon holds not; for if this were true
then every Knight, Citizen and Burgeſſe that ſerves for the
greateſt Counties, Cities and Burroughs, ſhould have a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
voyce and power in the Commons houſe, then thoſe that
ſerve for leſſer, and the ſmalleſt, becauſe they repreſent,
and aſſent, and vote for more Freeholders, Citizens and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſers
then they; and by the ſame reaſon, the leſſer and poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
Peers ſhould have a leſſer voyce in the Peers houſe then the
greateſt and richeſt; which we know is falſe and abſurd. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
many Peers are of greater worth, value, eſtate and
intereſt in relation to the Kingdom, then many poor Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs;
and therefore by this reaſon their voices ſhould be
greater then both Burgeſſes ſerving for them. Thirdly, every
Peer votes not onely for himſelf, but for all the Nobility and
whole State and Kingdom whereof he is a member, as well
and as much as any Commoner; and therefore his voyce is as
great as theirs.</p>
            <p>As to the Lords negative voice in Parliament, I anſwer,
firſt, the King, common Laws and Statutes of <hi>England,</hi> have
ever allowed and acknowledged it in all Ages: Secondly, to
deny them this Priviledge, is to make the whole houſe of Peers
meaner then the meaneſt Burgeſſe, who hath a negative voyce
in all debates and votes that paſſe the Commons houſe; yea,
to deny them to be freemen, and make them worſe then the
Philiſtine Lords, who had a negative voyce, 1 <hi>Sam. 29. 2, to</hi> 12
And to make them give their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſents to whatever the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115569:14"/>
ſhall carry by their plurality of Votes (though it be but by
one or two) is to ſet up Popiſh blind obedience, and implicit
faith, yea, to deſtroy that liberty of conſcience and judgement
which the Objectors, Levellers and Army do pretend they
fight, and ſo earneſtly conteſt for. Thirdly, there are ſundry
preſidents in our Parliament Rolls, of the Lords negative
voyces in Parliaments; I ſhall inſtance onely in two or three,
The firſt in print, in the Statute of <hi>Marlbridge, 20 H.</hi> 3. c. 3. <hi>The
Biſhops and Clergie importuned the Lords, that they would conſent, that
all ſuch as were born afore Matrimony ſhould be legitimate, as well as
thoſe who were born within Matrimony, as to the ſucceſſion of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
for ſo much as the Church accepteth ſuch for legitimate. And</hi> ALL
THE EARLS AND BARONS WITH ONE VOICE
anſwered, NOLUMUS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> WE WILL NOT CHANGE
THE LAWS OF THE REALM <hi>which hither to have been uſed
and approved.</hi> Here the Lords negative voyce hindered the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of the common Law, againſt the Biſhops and Clergies
importunate Vote to change it. So in the Parliament of 28 <hi>E.</hi>
3. nu. 25. the Commons deſired, <hi>that any man attainted upon a writ
of Oyer and Terminer, might bring his Attaint hanging the ſuits againſt
the other.</hi> To this the anſwer on the Roll is, THE LORDS
WILL NOT ALTER THE ORDER OF THE LAW.
The like negative anſwer you may read in 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 12, 29. 1 <hi>R.</hi>
2. n. 34, 69, 111. 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 57, 58. Parl. 1. &amp; Parl. 2. n. 48. and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
other Rols. Therefore to inferre any thing from theſe
erronious paſſages againſt the Lords Louſe, Votes, Judicature
or negative voyce, is but the blind following of the blind, and
contradict all Parliament Records, Hiſtory, Antiquity and
Law it ſelf, and approve and eſtabliſh their authority, judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and diſtinction from the Commoners.</p>
            <p>Finally, it is evident by the Parliament Rols of 6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl.
2. n. 3. 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Par. 2. n. 7, 8. 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 6, 7, 9, 17, 18, 35, 37. 17 <hi>E.</hi>
3. n. 9, 11, 12, 59. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 10. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 4, 5, 70. 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 3, 4,
29. 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 2. n. 6, 7. 27 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 4. 29 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 10. 36 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 6,
7. 40 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 8. 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 7. 47 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 5, 6, 12. 50 <hi>E.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. n. 3, 8, 9, 10
14. 51 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 18, 19. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 12, 13. 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 10, 23, to 29. 2 <hi>R.</hi>
2. Parl. 2. n. 6. 4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 9, to 16. 5 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 13, to 31. 6 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 9,
10, 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 6 <hi>R.</hi> 2. parl. 2. n. 14, 15. 6 <hi>R.</hi> 2. parl. 3. n. 8, 9. 7 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 11.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115569:14"/>
7 <hi>R.</hi> 2. Parl. 2. n. 10, 11. 13 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 6. 15 <hi>R.</hi> 2 n. 15. 16 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 6.
17 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 6, 17, 18 20 <hi>R. 2. 8, 9, 10, 12, 13, 16, 17. 21 R.</hi> 2. n. 8, 9,
16, to 21. That the Lords and Commons in the Parliaments
of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, were <hi>distinct
both in their debates, con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ultations, councels, p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>titions, votes, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of ſitting too, 50 E.</hi> 3. n. 3, 8. Sir <hi>John Knevet</hi> Chancellour of
<hi>England,</hi> having declared the cauſes of calling that Parliament
before the King, Lords and Commons, willed them to goe
together, THE LORDS BY THEMSELVES, AND THE
COMMOS BY THEMSELVES, and ſpeedily to conſult
and give anſwer. After which the Commons were willed to
d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>part TO THEIR ACCUSTOMED PLACE, b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the
Chapter houſe of the Abbot of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> whither they went.
In which place they likewiſe ſate, 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 10. &amp; 4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 9.
And in 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 17. 47 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 5, 6. 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 8. 9. 51 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 18,
19. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 12, 13, 14. 5 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 14. 6 <hi>R.</hi> 2. Parl. 2. n. 15. 7 <hi>R.</hi> 2.
Parl. 2. n. 10, 11. <hi>The Commons came to</hi> THE LORDS HOUSE,
<hi>and required that certain of the Lords, there named,</hi> WOULD
VOUCHSAFE TO CONFER WITH THE COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS;
<hi>whereupon they went to the Chamberlains chamber to confer
with the Commons: And at other times they were appointed to goe and
conſult with the Commons at ſome other place by the Lords order. In</hi>
2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. Parl. 1. n. 23. <hi>the Commons required, that ſome five or ſix of
the Lords might be appointed to come and diſcourſe with them;</hi> THE
LORDS DENIED THAT, ſaying, <hi>The ſame was the guiſe of
two or three Parliaments before.</hi> But the uſe was, <hi>That the Lords
ſhould among themſelves chooſe a certain number, and the Commons the
like, and that they ſhould confer together, which they would do: for if the
Commons would not diſſever themſelves, neither would they the Lords:
To the which order the Commons agreed.</hi> And 4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 10. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
deſiring the King that certain ſpeciall Lords might be aſſigned to
treat with them about affairs for the common benefit of the Realm: It
was condeſcended unto, with this protestation ſpecially entred by the Kings
command, that it ought not to be done of right</hi> OR CUSTOME,
BUT ONELY OUT OF THE KINGS SPECIALL
GRACE; which the Commons then acknowledged.</p>
            <p>A pregnant evidence both of their diſtinct Houſes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations,
except onely at private Committees and Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115569:15"/>
Yea, the Commons had anciently ſuch an high eſteem
of the Lords fidelity, wiſdom, abilities, councel and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
that in 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 17. <hi>The Commons pray that unto the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday
then next enſuing, the Articles they then preſented to the King,
might be committed to certain Earls, Barons, Biſhops and other</hi> WISE
MEN <hi>there named by them,</hi> TO BE AMENDED: <hi>which t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e
King granted.</hi> And in 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parl. 1. n. 11. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 5. 7 <hi>R.</hi> 2.
Parl. 2. n. 19, 20. 17 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 17. and ſundry other Rolls, The
Commons profeſſe THEIR INABILITY AND INSUFFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIENCY
TO ADVISE THE KING in ſome MATTERS
OF PEACE, WARRE, and ſafeguard of the Seas, for that
THEY PASSED THEIR CAPACITY, AND UNDER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOOD
NOT THE TERMS OF THE CIVILL LAW,
and ſome words in Truces: and therefore WHOLLY RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FERRED
THEMSELVES in theſe things to THE KING
AND THE LORDS, AND THE KINGS COUNSELL,
to do therein as they ſhould ſeem meet, being men of greater
wiſdom and experience in State-affairs of this nature, then
themſelves, in which they had little or no inſight. And in
2 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 11. <hi>The whole houſe of Commons claim, and the King grants
and confirms;</hi> and in 9 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 21. (entituled, <hi>The indempnity of
the Lords and Commons) The Lords and Commons ſeriouſly claim this
as a ſpeciall ancient priviledge belonging to both the Houſes, to ſit and
debate upon things in Parliament ſeverally by themſelves in their diſtinct
Houſes, in the Kings abſence</hi> (whoſe preſence might over-awe
them, and hinder their free debates;) <hi>which they both claimed, and
the king confirmed to them</hi> IN ALL TIMES TO COME, <hi>and
that no report ſhould be made to the King of any debate, vote or ayde
granted, till the Lords and Commons be all agreed, and that by</hi> THE
SPEAKERS MOUTHES. Which ancient priviledge ſo long
ſince claimed, granted, confirmed and enjoyed ever ſince, not
onely proves the ancient diſtinction of both houſes, but utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſubverts the Levellers project, who would ſtrip both Houſes
at once of this great priviledge, which the Commons deemed
their greateſt immunity (ſeeing they durſt ſpeak their mindes,
and vote more freely among themſelves, then in the preſence
of the King and Lords, for fear of incurring their diſpleaſures)
by reducing both houſes into one. The ſerious conſideration
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115569:15"/>
whereof, and of the premiſes, will I truſt for ever take them
off from their dangerous abſurd deſigne of Levelling and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing
the Lords Houſe to the Commons, and lay the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
illiterate proſecutors of it, levell with the duſt: the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
becauſe the King and Lords in Parliament, have not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
joyntly and ſeverally judged Commoners themſelves in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
for ſuch Treaſons, &amp; other miſdemeanours as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
triable in Parliament, not at the common Law, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
by<note n="r" place="margin">4 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 3, to 8. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 65 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 15, to 38. 1 <hi>R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 2. n 35, to 44 4 <hi>R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 2. n. 17, to 25 7 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 15, to 26. &amp;c.</note> infinite Preſidents; but even Knights of the Shire,
and other Members of the Commons Houſe it ſelf, in point
of miſdemeanours, undue Elections, and priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
as is appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by 16 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 6, 13, 14. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Phillip Courtney's</hi> caſe,
returned one of the Knights for the County of <hi>Devon, 17 R.</hi> 2.
n. 23. <hi>Roger de Swinerton's</hi> caſe, 5 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 4. n. 38. <hi>Thomas Thorp.</hi> his caſe,
elected knight for the County of <hi>Rotland,</hi> whoſe election was
heard, examined and adjudged by the Lords in Parliament to
be good, at the Commons requeſt; and 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. n. 25, to 30.
Baron <hi>Thorp's</hi> caſe, Speaker of the Commons houſe, whoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge
was ſolemnly debated before, and adjudged againſt
him by the Lords in Parliament; who therupon by the King's
direction, commanded the Commons to chooſe and preſent a
new Speaker; which they accordingly did the next day. Yea,
the whole Houſe of Commons in the Parliament of 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n.
79. Remonſtrated to the King, and voluntarily confeſſed. That
THE JUDGMENTS IN PARLIAMENT APPERTAIN
ONELY TO THE KING AND TO THE LORDS, and
NOT UNTO THE COMMONS; and that THE KING
AND LORDS EVER HAD IN ALL TIMES, AND
SHALL HAVE OF RIGHT THE JUDGEMENTS IN
PARLIAMENT: And the King then declared to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
that this Order ſhall be obſerved and kept IN ALL
TIMES TO COME, and that in caſes of Commoners and
Members of the Commons houſe it ſelf, as well as of Peers; as
is cleer by <hi>Thorp's</hi> caſe forecited, and by 5 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 71, 78. the
printed Statute of 5 <hi>H.</hi> 4. c. 6. <hi>Richard Chedders</hi> caſe, and 4 <hi>H.</hi> 8.
c. 8. <hi>Richard Strode</hi> his caſe, Burgeſſe for <hi>Plimton</hi> in the County
of <hi>Devon;</hi> where the <hi>King and Lords at the Prayer and Petition of the
Commons, provide remedies againſt the breaches of the priviledges of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115569:16"/>
Commons themſelves and their ſervants, which themſelves alone had no
ſufficient power r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right and determine; the power of judicature being
not in them, but in the King, Lords and houſes of Peers alone;</hi> who
long before the Conqueſt had the power of Judicature, as is
evident by <hi>Brampton,</hi> and Maſter<note n="*" place="margin">Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, part 2. c. 5. ſect. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Selden,</hi> in the caſe of Earl
<hi>Goodwin,</hi> in a Parliament held in the yeer 1052. wherein <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
the Confeſſor appealed to THE EARLS AND BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RONS
againſt this Earl, for the murther of his Brother <hi>Alfred</hi>
in theſe words, <hi>Domini</hi> COMITES <hi>&amp;</hi> BARONES <hi>terrae, &amp;c.
Volo quod inter Nos in iſta appellatione</hi> RECTUM JUDICIUM
DECERNETIS <hi>&amp;</hi> DEBITAM JUSTITIAM FACIATIS.
And therfore it is the very extremity of injuſtice to deny them
this their ancient Heredetary right, and priviledge now, and
transfer it to the Commons houſe, who never enjoyed it in
any former Age, and can make no right, nor lawfull claim
unto it at this preſent.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 3. line 1. <hi>H.</hi> 7. read <hi>H.</hi> 4.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
